Hello,
hello. Can y'all hear me?
Yes.
Excellent.
We'll just wait one minute to get things going.
Making sure I'm recording. Whoops, didn't mean to go to that
yet.
Okay, it's 6:30, so we'll go ahead and get started.
Today, we're going to be talking about the vacuum
environment, and we kind of touched on this
the first lesson. But,
we did cover last time
solutions to the multi or
MMOD,
micrometeoroid and orbital debris solutions.
And I do have a little article from SpaceX that I wanted to share with y'all.
So I'll do that first. We learned that the debris,
we did it to ourselves. Micrometeoroids, not much we can
do about it except design our spacecraft to survive it, and
Whipple shields were a good solution, and y'all
got to look at that in the last homework.
So this time, we're looking at the vacuum environment.
Of course, there's nothing in space.
So we have learned over the past few weeks that
there's a lot in space that we need to be concerned
about that we're not protected from when we're
on Earth.
However, it's still much more of a vacuum than we have
here. As an example, at 100 kilometers or the
Kármán line, the pressure is six times
less than at sea level.
Six times less, and satellites travel much higher than
that. So,
I've been getting asked a lot of questions about the final
project. No, it's worth 25% of our final grade.
All it is, is a complete report
documenting the design project from beginning to end.
So, don't write it like your two separate milestones.
I want a complete cohesive report, although
almost all of the work that you have put into
the milestones will be relevant to the final project.
So, that's why I don't announce this four weeks ago,
because
you really cannot work on the final project until you get milestone two done, and
I do plan on returning that fairly
quickly so that you can update the
milestones. The whole purpose of the milestones was to get
you to a final report that hopefully I've already read
three times,
and it'll be awesome.
Because if you're incorporating the feedback from the milestones, updating it,
and writing it as a professional report, you should have no
problem with the final project. And it is due the last day of
class, so I'll have a busy weekend on 8/8 and
8/9.
Okay. This is one thing I wanted to talk about.
This article just came out. This was three days ago as of
yesterday.
Every SpaceX Starlink satellite has to dodge a collision
almost weekly,
and that means there have been
355,000
about collision avoidance maneuvers just in the
past year,
which is up by
about three times in 2024.
This is from the semi-annual report from
December 25 through May 26.
They had
207,152
maneuvers. The previous half year, June
25 through November 25, they had
148,696. So,
that is quite a bit more.
So, the
problem or the issue is multiplying
substantially
every six months now. So, I think that's
notable. That's something we really need to be paying attention to.
Each Starlink satellite did more than 40
space-dodging maneuvers per year last
year,
and they initiate a maneuver whenever there's...
They might be a little more stringent
than others, but whenever there's a three in 10 million chance,
they will go ahead and do the maneuver.
So if you add this to
the Kuiper, or whatever Amazon is calling it now,
constellation,
China's Guifen or Thousand Cells constellation,
this is a significant change in the way we were
doing things even five years ago.
Okay. So with that, we're going to start with Garrett
Kennedy's.
Any comments or questions on that
before I go to Garrett's
presentation?
Here we go. All right.
Let me share this.
Cold welding, right, Garrett?
That's right. Cold welding.
All right. Take it away.
All right.
So, my name is Garrett Kennedy, presenting on cold welding in the vacuum
environment. So,
we're going to talk a little bit about what cold welding is.
We're going to talk about what are called mechanisms of
exposure, a specific incident that actually happened regarding
cold welding that caused a failure on orbit, and then
what methods we use to mitigate this issue, prevent
cold welding from happening. So first, two slides,
please.
What is cold welding?
Cold welding is basically this phenomenon that I characterize in a really
simplistic sense as metals are like Play-Doh.
Obviously, not the same as Play-Doh, but when we have two
metals that are completely clean surfaces.
The nature of metals that makes them ductile and malleable,
that interatomic interaction also means that when we have
two clean pieces of metal in contact with one another, there's
no real meaningful differentiation between those pieces of metal.
Which means that if those conditions occur, we can basically have
two pieces of metal fused together with very little pressure, just having surface
contact. Now, the amount of stickiness to
that bond will depend on time, and it will depend on pressure between the
two pieces of metal,
but this is something we really want to avoid when it comes to spacecraft.
Slide, please.
So a visual demonstration here. On the surface of Earth, we don't often
see cold welding. It does occur, but it's kind of a niche case, which I'll talk
about later.
Because we have, say you had an iron ingot or a steel beam
or what have you, all of the oxygen available in the
atmosphere is constantly doing a very light layer of oxidation
on the outside of that piece of metal.
So the two pieces of metal, we take them on Earth and we put them together, and
they don't just fuse together because they have this very thin
shell of oxidized metal, which doesn't have that same
set of properties that metal has. So they remain two separable
pieces.
If we don't have that thin oxidized layer, what
we see is those two pieces of metal fuse together like Play-Doh.
So you might say, now why wouldn't we just build all of these
components on the ground, not in vacuum, so we have that thin
layer of oxidized metal so the pieces don't fuse
together if they come in contact when we're in vacuum?
The thing is, we do. Slide, please.
What we see is that--
Slide, please.
What we see is that we run into issues with the surfaces of the metal
getting damaged, and as soon as we damage the surface of the metal when we're in
vacuum, now we have some exposed
non-oxidized metal
that's not going to re-oxidize because we don't have available oxygen.
And there's different effects that have names for this,
but this is the real danger when it comes to cold welding on orbit.
Because for the most part, once again, we already have that very thin oxidized
layer, but if we start having metal pieces come into contact with one another,
they're going to do small amounts of damage to each other just by these natural
processes of coming into contact, and they're going to
expose that non-oxidized metal, and that's where we get cold
welding.
Slide, please.
So there's four primary categories of surface
damaging. The first one here on the left, galling, is
actually where we see cold welding occur on the ground, and we see this in really
tight-fitting, well-machined bolts and screws.
So you get this tight fit and you're driving the screw in and the two surfaces of
metal are scraping against each other, kind of removing that
oxidized metal. And because the fit's so tight, we get
cold welding occurring because there's not enough oxygen available to
re-oxidize that surface quickly enough.
So galling is the one example that we tend to see on the ground.
Bending would be like bending a piece of wire, where because the
properties of that oxidized metal aren't the same as the non-oxidized metal, the
surface cracks and exposes.
Fretting would just be like vibration while in contact, and then impact
is pretty self-explanatory. One piece impacts another, and we get
exposure of that metal and potential for cold welding.
Slide, please.
So the one really big notable incident of cold welding occurring
on orbit and causing a failure is in 1991,
three of the ribs for the high-gain antenna for
Galileo failed to deploy. In retrospect, we figured out
that this was a result of cold welding, specifically because of fretting.
So the vibration that was happening during launch and transfer into its
orbit ended up exposing some of that non-oxidized metal,
and cold-welded those ribs to the frame that they were attached to in their folded
configuration.
Generally, we don't see that there's a ton of cold welding
issues on orbit because it's a known phenomenon.
In fact, this has been known about-- It was characterized first in the
1940s. So people have known about this a long time, and there's a
lot of care put into avoiding having issues with cold welding.
So we don't tend to see a bunch of issues, but this was a really notable example of
that happening and causing a failure. Slide, please.
So how do we mitigate this? How do we avoid it?
Well, you avoid metal-on-metal contact is the short version.
If it's impossible to avoid metal-on-metal contact in terms of the mechanisms that
we're using, we have to assess the
risk and we have to use coatings or surfaces to
separate those metal surfaces.
Cold welding databases that are available can give us a lot of information about
how much risk is posed by this particular
metal-on-metal contact. Different metals will have different amounts of bonding
depending on, again, time, depending on the amount of pressure between the two,
so on and so forth. And those databases can really give you a good idea
about what kind of risk is being presented by this potential
contact. Slide, please.
But since there are so many cases where we just can't avoid that metal-on-metal
contact,
we use techniques like applying grease, using washers or barriers,
and coatings. Now, grease tends to be a really good option for
non-separable contacts, meaning that if you have
grease between the two pieces of metal and the two pieces of metal are meant to
come apart, the grease is not going to work well.
It's going to actually make it harder to pull the pieces apart.
But it's really good if the pieces are constantly against each other, like
rotating or something like that.
We do tend to see issues with outgassing when it comes to grease, though.
So that is a big concern if we're looking at using grease.
Washers and barriers, things like ceramics and polymers are nice.
Nobody's ever seen them cold weld, so they tend to be a good
option for offering that barrier.
And then when we're talking about coatings,
the thicker the coating, the better off you are.
Obviously, there's limits to that for other reasons.
But one of the ideals that we're looking for with the coating is
that that coating gets integrated into the metal surface, like we see
with parkerization.
If you're familiar with that process, where we actually see a chemical reaction
where we get a lot of the coating integrated into the surface of the metal.
So even if we expose some of it, we still get a limited
amount of cold welding.
So
that's all I have for cold welding.
Looking forward to seeing the questions on the discussion board.
Professor,
you're muted if you're trying to talk.
Oh, thank you. I was sneezing and I turned it off.
So thank you for letting me know that. I thought it was going to be a question.
Okay, I'll repeat what I said.
So the Galileo mission is actually very fascinating
because there was a lot of things that went on during that.
It was originally supposed to launch on one of the launch
vehicles with an upper stage and go directly, I don't remember which one,
and go directly to Jupiter,
but it got remanifested to the
shuttle, I think it was Atlantis. And in
that, it didn't have enough velocity, delta V, to get there
directly, so they actually had to
project it inwards to get a gravitational assist off
of Venus,
to give it enough energy to get out to Jupiter.
So that very well could have been part of the issue
there,
is that they didn't plan-- That takes longer, too, to do gravity
assist, and also that heats things up a lot more when you're
going inward rather than outward from the Earth.
So there's a lot of intricacies that
are involved there. It's a fascinating story.
If you can get any videos on that, I encourage you to watch
that. And they ended up having to
use their low-gain antenna, the omnidirectional antenna,
because the high-gain antenna would not deploy.
So that was a big deal,
a big reduction in efficiency of the program.
The other thing, I like your explanation, your graphical
explanation of the parts and the layers coming
together, and also the mechanisms of exposure.
I really like that, too. So any other comments or questions?
Okay, thank you, Garrett.
Okay, the last three are videos, so let's take a look at
these videos.
Let me know if you cannot hear these.
The first one is by-- Jordan, are you here tonight?
I thought I saw him on.
Nope, I guess not. Okay, so we'll start with Jordan's, or
we'll go second with Jordan. So here we go.
Let me know if you cannot see this video.
Probably not, right? You're not seeing it?
Yeah, we can't see it.
Okay. I will stop sharing and share this new
screen.
Can you all see it now?
Yes.
Okay, great.
Real dangerous frettings-
Oops
... this tiny little-
Already watched half of it, so...
Hey there, everybody. My name is Jordan Clayton, and my current events topic is
the vacuum environment. I want to look at this through
one specific and slightly strange effect, and that would be cold welding,
where spacecraft parts can fuse themselves together in orbit with no heat at all.
All right.
So
in 2024, November of 2024, there was an experiment called
Astrobeat, went up into the International Space Station.
It had a goal to use cold welding on purpose as a way to patch holes
punched in the hull by debris. What's interesting is that cold welding
is normally a failure mode, something that designers fight to avoid,
and the same physics once jammed a famous NASA antenna shut.
So the question that I want to answer is pretty simple, just how do two metal
plates
or metal parts weld together in orbit with no heat and no welder?
Okay. So first, what the vacuum environment actually is.
So I think one way to conceptualize this a little bit more concretely
would be to look at some values, some measurements, so we can look at the
pressure drop. And the pressure drops about 13
orders of magnitude from the ground to low Earth orbit.
At the space station's altitude, it's around 10 to the minus 8 Torr,
which is a harder vacuum than most chambers we could build on the ground.
So the consequence that matters for us is there's essentially no
oxygen up there to regrow the oxide films that normally protect metal
surfaces from bonding together.
So why is clean metal sticky? So on Earth, every metal
instantly grows an oxide layer plus a film of
absorbed gas. Those films are what keeps the two parts from
bonding when they touch.
So a truly clean surface has a very high sticking coefficient,
and it wants to bond. In vacuum, once that protective film is scrubbed
away, it doesn't grow back. Now you have bare metal touching bare metal, and the
atoms form real metallic bonds across the joint.
So the two parts effectively become one crystal, because the atoms
can't tell which original piece they belong to.
No heat and no melting required.
So
pure static contact, two flat parts just resting together,
rarely cause cold welds because the real surfaces, when you zoom way,
way in, are rough and the oxide films usually
survive. The real danger is fretting, so that's tiny little
micro-oscillations very quickly, like you could experience in
launch or impact. That motion will scrub the film
off and it presses the fresh metal together, which
is essentially a friction weld. So the worst metal pairings,
if you're trying to avoid the cold welding phenomenon, are soft
metals like aluminum and copper and any metal against an
identical metal. But, as you can see from this
ESA test data, even dissimilar metals adhere with real
force once the film is breached.
So we'll take a look at a case study here,
Galileo's antenna. So this is kind of a classic story,
and in 1991, Galileo's umbrella-style
high-gain antenna tried to open, but it stalled with 3 of its 18 ribs
stuck. NASA's investigation found that the main cause was
loss of the dry molybdenum disulfide lubricant on
the rib pins, and that wore away by vibration during several
cross-country truck trips, combined with friction in the pin socket
joints.
It also never got a thermal vacuum test before the launch, so
cold welding of the now bare metal was certainly a contributor to the
sticking, but once the lubrication was gone.
So it was not a spontaneous static weld.
Lubrication loss and fretting came first, and set the
environment up for the static weld that occurred on
that particular scenario. So cold welding is real, but it
can be over-cited
as a cause of issues on the internet and doing research
around.
So I'll talk about both sides of that coin here.
And so on the confirmed and Occurrent slide, recent ESA
testing shows that repeatedly bending a wire harness, for example,
in vacuum can cold weld the individual strands together.
So that could stiffen the harness or even break wires.
On an over-blamed slide, we have NASA's Lucy
mission, which had a solar array stick at about
92% open in 2021. A lot of people blamed
vacuum sticking or cold welding, but NASA
actually traced it to a deployment lanyard that lost tension.
So the lesson being that cold welding is real, but careful diagnostic
matters, and not every stuck deployable is a cold or vacuum
weld.
Okay. So now we're going to go back to Astrobeat.
Mentioned briefly in the beginning, so turning that failure into a tool, which is,
I think, a pretty cool way to go about this.
So
it kind of flips the whole problem around.
Instead of preventing the cold welding, we're looking to actually use it on purpose
to patch hull damage from hypervelocity debris impacts.
It's a fairly mature demonstrator.
The technology readiness is level six, and it ran
on the space station by a team led out of Malta.
It went up on a SpaceX
rocket, and the same adhesion
that threatens the hinges and antennas becomes a repair method.
And the timing is quite good with all these mega
constellations that we're starting to see being implemented
and also put into future planning and growing debris
population. Being able to repair spacecraft in orbit is
becoming worth a lot more than ever right now and will probably
continue to grow in its importance as we move
forward in the future.
So how do designers actually fight this, the unwanted
cold welding, that is? There's four main
levers. Material choice. So we want to
avoid soft and identical metal pairs in any contact
that has to separate later.
And pair a hard metal against a soft metal.
That's a much better combination.
Second would be coatings and dry lubricants, like the molybdenum
disulfide. They help, but ESA testing did find that they're
certainly not a guarantee. The adhesion came back after only about
20 fretting cycles. A third lever would be
to limit fretting itself with preload and
really stiff hold-downs.
Adding redundant actuators so
one stuck joint is not totally fatal.
And then the fourth and final lever will be protecting the lubricant during the
ground handling, which is exactly where the Galileo failure occurred,
and qualify the deployment in a thermal vacuum chamber
before flight.
So takeaways to wrap up here, there are four main ones
that I'd like to cover. The vacuum environment is dangerous by
absence, with no oxide to regrow,
bare metal bonds, fretting and impact, not static contact are
what actually derive cold welding failures.
The effect is real, but frequently oversighted, and Lucy case
shows why you have to diagnose carefully.
And finally, engineers are now turning that into a tool, which is exactly what
Astrobee is testing on,
or tested on the space station, is planning an Astrobee
2 for further testing on that. So with that, that
is my current events presentation on the
vacuum environment.
Excellent. So a couple of takeaways I got from that.
Let me see my audio's on good. I
really like the application of Astrobee,
and to find out that there's a new mission coming up is pretty
cool. The other thing
is, well, cold welding on purpose is really cool.
And then he mentioned that some of the worst
materials were aluminum and copter, and some of the best
materials were, or one of the best materials was
molybdenum
disulfide.
And those are good materials to help protect.
And I'll get into that a little bit more in today's lecture.
Let's see, who's next?
We are going to go
to
Nick Danko. All right. We have four of them today,
so let me share my screen
again.
And here it is.
Hi, good evening. My name is Nick Danko.
It's my current events presentation on designing for the vacuum of space,
cover how the vacuum environment influences spacecraft materials, thermal
controls, and testing.
Probably the fourth presentation of the evening, so I think some of
this will be already covered by my predecessors.
To recap on the vacuum environment, space is not empty, it's just an
extreme low pressure. So at sea level, it's 101
kilopascals, but as we move to higher or much
lower pressures, we usually reference them in torr.
So at 760 torr, at low Earth orbit, it's 10 to the negative
6, down to 10 to the negative 9 torr.
And there's still trace amounts of atomic oxygen here.
So I started my career off in clean rooms doing optical thin films coating
and operating vacuum chambers. So this is kind of the level we would get to in
our chambers was 10 to the negative 6 or 10 to the negative 7, where
it is very low, but there's still trace amounts of atoms and
dust and stuff that can accumulate and get in the way at this level.
But when you move down to deep space, we're down below 10 to negative
12 torr, which is ultra-high vacuum, where pressure is near
zero and there's no medium at all. But here are the key effects of the
vacuum environment on your spacecraft.
Four ways, or the fourth is kind of an asterisk, but first one is
outgassing. Materials shed trapped gas that condense on optics,
sensors, and radiators.
Cold welding can occur, where bare metal surfaces can fuse on
contact, where there's no oxide layer between them.
And there's also no convection in vacuum because there's no air, and heat leaves
only by radiation. Nothing carries it away.
And the radiation and atomic oxygen are not
necessarily the vacuum environment itself.
We've covered those in the other environments.
But because we are in vacuum and there is no
atmosphere, it is
by
similar effects affected by the vacuum environment.
So here I have an explanation of what outgassing and cold welding are.
In a later slide, we'll cover the considerations on how to mitigate these.
But outgassing is when materials that have trapped
gases in them experience vacuum and then release those,
which can then cloud lenses and solar cells and other
sensitive surfaces. I observed this when I was working with vacuum chambers.
Somebody left a screwdriver in a chamber and pumped it down, and the
screwdriver outgassed and had plastic particles all over the chamber, and it
took over a month to get that cleaned out.
And cold welding is described here, but essentially there's no
oxide or air to separate metals. So then once they're in vacuum and they touch,
the atoms can become bonded together and it looks like a weld.
So the thermal behavior in a vacuum is very different.
Heat only moves by radiation. I think we're all familiar with that.
Convection is not possible, and then conduction only works
with mounted hardware. And the radiative exchange is governed by the
Stefan-Boltzmann law for equilibrium temperature.
This is further complicated with the extreme temperature
swings. Sometimes you want to be radiating
if you're getting too hot, or you don't want to if you're in a cold environment.
So controlling
these materials and where the heat goes and when it gets radiated is very important
in vacuum.
Then here we get into the design responses for engineering
and the structuring mechanisms. So you want to use qualified materials that
are low outgassing, so that those gases aren't released, contamination.
But then you also vacuum bake these components before flight.
You want to be aware
to vent trapped gas, even if you have low outgassing materials.
If you have some sort of enclosure where there's just air in there, as the
pressure decreases
as you ascend into space towards vacuum, that trapped gas will
expand and break or shatter whatever it's
contained by. And then you want to use dry lubrication.
So special space greases
are used to make sure they don't outgas.
As we've mentioned, controlling the temperature with the severe temperature
swings to hot to cold is very important.
So we use a combination of passive and active controls, different thermal
blankets, radiators, and heat pipes to move heat and reject it
passively. But then you can use active
electric heaters and thermostats and louvers when you're in the
cold cases. And then you want to qualify this
from your design to test in thermal vacuum chambers, so called TVAC
chambers, where you cycle through hot and cold
to mimic that space environment in vacuum, and you
can see how different components are performing or where the heat is, and you
can redesign as needed. So in summary, you really need to design
from the vacuum up. You need to treat it as your active environment, where there's
going to be no cooling, materials are going to outgas, your
clean metal surfaces may cold weld, and you're going to have violent temperature
swings. So the design needs to take all these into
consideration using the parts we talked about
for low outgassing materials, vent pass, so no trapped airs in there,
dry lubricants, and a combination of active and passive thermal controls.
And then finally, TVAC testing is very important to just bake out and
outgas all your materials, but also validate that your as-built model matches
your thermal design, where nothing is
exceeding its temperature profile that it's rated
for. So that's it for my current events
presentation on design considerations for the vacuum environment.
Here are some of my references. Thank you.
All right. So that was a very informative
session there.
I do want to point out a couple of things.
The parameters that he was talking about as far as outgassing,
TML, and CVCM, we're going to go over in
tonight's lecture. The other thing is
for the thermal environment. We're going to do a couple
examples
about that tonight. And then I thought
it was really interesting, I did not know that leaving a
screwdriver in a TVAC chamber would have such
large impacts
on the chamber itself. So,
I appreciated that example. Any other comments or questions?
Okay, we will go to...
Whoops.
This is our last presentation, Paige Malden,
and I will share it with you before I start it.
And this is number four for tonight.
Yeah. This is the right one.
Hi, everyone. I'm Paige Malden. My current events topic is vacuum
environment and spacecraft design considerations.
I'm using Blue Origin's Blue Moon Mark 1 lunar lander as the current
example. It recently completed thermal vacuum testing at NASA
Johnson Space Center. The main question I'm focusing on is simple:
Why does vacuum testing matter before a spacecraft flies?
For the current event, NASA announced in May 2026 that Blue
Origin's Blue Moon Mark 1 lunar lander completed environmental
testing. The testing was done inside Chamber A at NASA Johnson Space
Center. That chamber was used to recreate vacuum
conditions and extreme hot and cold temperatures.
Engineers used the test to check how the lander performed before it is expected to
operate near the Moon. The important point is that
this was real flight hardware being tested against real environmental
concerns. So this is not just a textbook topic.
It's something spacecraft programs still have to prove before launch.
To understand why this matters, it helps to look at what vacuum changes for a
spacecraft.
Space is often described as empty, but empty does not mean harmless.
A spacecraft in vacuum is surrounded by very little pressure.
That means trapped gas inside panels, covers, or small volumes can
expand unless it has a controlled way to vent.
Vacuum also removes convection. On Earth, air can carry heat
away from warm hardware. In space, that doesn't happen.
Heat has to move through the spacecraft by conduction or leave the
spacecraft by radiation. Another issue is outgassing.
Some materials release trapped gases or volatile compounds when placed in
vacuum. Those molecules can move through vacuum and deposit on colder
surfaces. For a spacecraft, that can create contamination concerns for
optics, sensors, thermal controlled surfaces, and solar arrays.
So the vacuum environment affects structures, thermal control, and material
selection.
I grouped the main risks into three simple areas.
The first is thermal control. Space is cold in some ways, but spacecraft
can still overheat. Electronics, batteries, and instruments generate
heat, and that heat cannot be removed by surrounding air.
The second risk is outgassing and contamination.
This matters because even a thin film on an optical surface, a
radiator, or a solar array can reduce performance.
This is especially important for missions with sensors or cameras.
The third risk is pressure and material behavior.
Trapped volumes need vent paths. Seals, lubricants, adhesives,
and mechanisms may behave differently in vacuum than they do on the ground.
So the design concern is not only whether the spacecraft survives, the
spacecraft also has to stay clean, thermally stable,
and functional over the mission. This is where thermal
vacuum testing becomes important.
A chamber like NASA's Chamber A is used to recreate some of the major conditions a
spacecraft will experience. The chamber can provide high vacuum,
and it can also create hot and cold boundary conditions.
During testing, engineers can operate hardware in a more flight-like environment.
They watch temperatures, structural behavior, electronics, software responses, and
subsystem performance. The goal is to find problems while the spacecraft is still
on the ground. For example, a test could show one component gets too hot,
or that the material behaves unexpectedly, or that the thermal model needs to be
updated. Finding that during ground testing is much better than
discovering it after launch when the vehicle's already in space and much harder to
fix.
Design responses are fairly practical.
First, engineers select low outgassing materials.
That reduces the chance that the released materials will contaminate sensitive
surfaces. Second, hardware may be baked out before final integration or
flight.
That helps drive off volatile materials early instead of letting it release later
near the spacecraft. Third, designers provide controlled vent
paths. That prevents trapped gas from creating pressure loads inside
enclosed spaces. Fourth, mechanisms and lubricants have to
be vacuum compatible. A mechanism that works normally on Earth may
not behave the same way in vacuum. Thermal control hardware is also
a major part of design. That can include insulation,
heaters, radiators, thermal straps, and conductive paths.
Finally, thermal vacuum testing checks whether or not all those choices
work together.
The overall goal is to keep the spacecraft clean, thermally stable,
structurally safe, and functional in flight-like vacuum conditions.
The main takeaway is that vacuum is not just the absence of air.
It changes how a spacecraft transfers heat, changes how the material releases
contaminants, and it changes how pressure inside trapped volumes behaves.
Blue Moon Mark 1 is a current example of why these effects are still important for
spacecraft design. Before a spacecraft flies, engineers need
evidence that the design can operate under realistic environmental conditions.
That's why thermal vacuum testing is such an important step before
launch. Thank you. I'm happy to take any questions.
Okay, and that was our last current events presentation.
I did appreciate the Blue Moon Mark 1 example.
I think that's very relevant to what we're doing, and
I do have to say that Paige went into
probably more detail than I'm going to go into tonight about design
solutions, so that was very thorough.
I did want to, while I'm pulling up my charts,
say that UCCS, my Space
Systems Lab students, are currently
in
Palestine, Texas, doing
vibration, static testing, and TVAC
testing on an experiment that we're getting ready to
fly in August from Fort Sumner, New
Mexico, called On a High Altitude Space Platform.
And as part of that, we had to
go through all the testing requirements, and I found out
just today we're going to launch in the
early August,
and it'll be a 20-hour flight experiment,
about 20, however long the balloon lasts, on
a high altitude platform that
will provide an opportunity to get
radiation. And what we're looking at doing
is using a special type of polymer to
enclose the electronics, one exposed, one not
exposed, with Geiger counters both inside the
polymer enclosure and
outside the polymer enclosure, and compare the performance of the two.
We just went through successful vibration testing yesterday,
or day before yesterday. Today, I just found
out that
one of our Geiger counters failed in TVAC.
So that's very important to find out on the
ground before we launch, so we have an
opportunity to replace those components that aren't as
robust against the space environment
before we actually launch it. It would be horrible if we launched it and the Geiger
counter
quit working when we're on
the space platform.
But the TVAC testing that we did ahead of time helped
us to prevent that from going.
So look for updates. As soon as we launch
it and successfully complete it, we've got a couple of papers coming out about
it, but we'll probably have some type of news article come about it too,
so keep a look out for that.
If you didn't catch the name, it is Space...
Whoops.
My pen's not working, of course.
And I do need to get my pen working
Okay, a little bit of technical difficulties here. Let's see.
How do I get out of this?
And it doesn't help that my delete key is broken.
Let me try Task Manager to get out,
and then I'll be back
with the PowerPoint in just a minute.
Zoom and my PowerPoint do not seem to be getting along together
tonight. So
let me end that task.
Okay.
So let's share again.
And we were on slide, this one.
Okay. So if you're looking out for information on
that, it is called the High Altitude Space Platform,
done from my Space Systems lab at
UCCS,
and it's launching early August.
And that is a radiation protection experiment with polymers.
Yep.
So we talked about how
operating in a vacuum is dangerous.
All of our speakers talked about these four
effects: solar UV degradation, heat transfer,
outgassing, and cold welding. We're going to dig into those a little
more tonight.
First off, solar UV degradation.
How much of a vacuum is it?
Well, as was pointed out by one of the speakers, I don't
remember which one, it's about 13
orders of magnitude less in LEO
than at sea level. So this is pretty significant.
A vacuum can be good in some ways, less drag, for
example, but it
happens to not affect everything
positively. Only about 21% of the
sun's energy passes through the atmosphere,
31% is reflected, 29% is scattered,
and 19%, good for us,
is absorbed as heat. Mostly,
the ones that are filtered out are the ones in the very low
wavelength range. Gamma rays, X-rays.
X-rays are a little higher than that.
Some UV.
And much of that is absorbed by the ozone layer here.
So you can see that this filters out a lot of that.
Well, when you're in space, that doesn't happen.
Notice the max output from the sun is about 0.5
micrometers, and the visible spectrum is about
0.37 to 0.7 on this
graph, so this would be visible.
Infrared would be right after that,
0.7 to 1.4
roughly kind of covers the infrared
range.
And UV is 0.1 to
0.4.
Well, and some of that's very high energy particles too.
So, whoops, I went on to the next page.
On orbit, though, you can get pretty much the full
strength of the whole spectrum per
the curve given by
this estimate here.
You can get pretty much all of that affecting you.
So a little more about solar UV degradation. What can that do?
That can cause some of our bonds for our chemicals
that are
combined together to become
single
chemicals.
And the way that happens is, first off, we have
energy of a single photon, and we can
calculate that. So the energies here...
Whoops, let me move this out of the way.
The energies here, bond energy at 25 degrees Celsius,
are given for the single bonds, and I'll explain what that
is in case you're a little rusty,
of between 1.52 and
3.73 electron
volts. And we talked about what an electron volt was before.
So
one thing to note, some textbooks do use
For frequency,
they do use the little symbol
nu,
which I don't use because I teach astrodynamics and nu is
usually true anomaly.
H is Planck's constant,
and that's given here.
Table represents how much energy it takes to break a bond in
electron volts, and if you don't remember,
a electron volt is
six point... Well, I have it here. An
electron volt...
No, I don't. One electron volt is
1.6021, just in case you need
additional significant figures.
So be careful if you're working homework problems to convert
electron volts to joules to be compatible
with
this equation.
Sometimes this energy can be large enough to break the chemical
energy bonds, especially for the weaker bonds, which are the single
ones.
And in a single bond, each atom provides one valence
electron or outer electron. So
let me explain a little bit about how that happens.
We will take, whoops, carbon-carbon,
and on the periodic table, carbon has
this symbol, which means it
has
six
protons, six electrons. We're going to talk about electrons here.
This is a
2D representation of a 3D phenomenon, by the
way. So in the inner electron bond, we get
two. That's the max it can hold. Three, four,
five, and then a sixth. Another carbon comes
on,
completes that bond there by
sharing the electron, and they become
what's called a single bond there.
Oxygen can do the same thing. Oxygen is eight on
the periodic table. So we would have
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
Another oxygen bond comes along. One, two, three, four,
five, six, seven, eight. They share a
bond.
Double bond, on the other hand, each atom shares two
pair of valence electrons, one from each atom.
So for example, C6
carbon,
we have
one, two, three, four,
five,
six. Whoops, I didn't spread those out well enough. Oh, well.
And then from our other carbon bond or other
carbon item,
we have those. So they share those two electrons,
and it turns out to break an electron, you might
want to write this down,
wavelengths less than 0.36
micrometers. And those can break carbon bonds,
single carbon bonds
immediately.
And
wavelengths less than 0.82
micrometers
can break, this would be carbon bonds,
O-O bonds.
And you're going to show in homework
six
problems one and two, that this is the case.
So I got a couple of assignments. I'll go over those in just a
minute.
Atomic oxygen can also cause damage to polymers and coatings, as
you can see here and all along the outskirts
of here.
They're very susceptible to atomic oxygen.
Solar panels can also be
impacted as received and after
exposure. You can see a lot of degradation there due to
atomic oxygen.
Beta
cloth liners
on the shuttle was supposed to help
protect against atomic oxygen. We currently
use beta cloth liners on the ISS and
spacesuits,
but you might ask, well, is that really relevant to today's
spacecraft?
So
it also affects the thermal control surfaces.
So if you do something to protect against atomic
oxygen, it's also going to affect your thermal control
system. So what are beta cloth liners?
Shown on the left here and shown on the shuttle
bays there.
They're glass fibers
dipped in Teflon and polysilicon,
and they have good thermal and chemical stability on the
Earth. Bond energy of about six electron volts, which
is relatively high. It's obviously a double
bond. However
Since the shuttle operated above the ozone layer in the
thermosphere, the high
energy wavelengths and
high frequency small wavelengths are prevalent.
So that's why you still get some of these effects up at that
altitude. So I wanted to take a minute to talk
about homework six. I showed this to
my undergraduate students in class
on Monday, and they were like, "Wait a minute, there's three parts just for
part D." And I'm like, "Yeah. There is.
You're right."
But this isn't really a hard exercise, but I think it's very informative.
First off,
from the equation E
equals...
Whoops, that's the next one.
E equals HC over
lambda
based on the carbon-carbon
bond,
and you'll want to convert the electron volts to joules
here,
3.47 electron volts.
You will solve for the wavelength, and like I said before, it
should be less than
0.36, roughly. Round off error.
Then you're going to make a linear approximation.
This is straight from the Tribble textbook, and this is
the estimated
irradiance of the sun and the units are, just to make
clear, watts per centimeter squared
micrometers because we're dealing with the wavelength in
micrometers. Now, for the wavelength of
interest, that starts at about .2.
.34 is about here.
Drew my line a little crooked. You can approximate this as a
straight line.
So what I'd like you to do is approximate that as a straight line
using your math principles and
evaluate, and I'll tell
you, first off, get a straight line approximation.
That's part B.
Then integrate the ratio of the solar
radiance divided by the photon energy over the
wave band of interest to estimate the number of
photons. So you're going to take
S as a function of lambda,
which is wavelength over E,
D lambda
and approximate that where we know from
before
E is equal to HC over lambda. So you'll end up with a
lambda squared term in the numerator,
and you will integrate that,
and that will give the approximate
number of photons per second that the Earth
sees or receives from the sun in that
range of wavelengths. Part D is then estimate the
total number of photons from the sun.
Now, you can use any method you want.
This is just one method that I recommend.
Find the average photon energy. You know that the sun
is at a specific temperature. You can estimate the maximum
wavelength, which should be about, I think, about
.5 micrometers.
And then you can assume
solar luminosity, find the number of photons per
second and then convert
that to
your answer from part
two and divide by 4pi R squared, where R is the
distance to the Earth. Now, this is only one method.
If you have another method to come up with a number, not
assuming a perfect black body necessarily from
this, but if you can find another reference that gives
you the number of photons per--
I think the units I used was centimeter squared.
Yeah. Centimeter squared, watts per centimeter squared.
Feel free to use that and just make sure you reference your
source, and this is an opinion-based one so everyone
should,
you provide good rationale, do you think this is a significant
risk?
In homework problem three, you're going to compare
this to a black body. Does
that say that here, black body approximation?
100%
absorptivity, 100% emissivity. So
perfect doesn't really exist in the real world.
But you're going to assume a black body
and come up with a
distribution of the irradiance.
So here's your expression for this with respect to
the wavelength.
So what you're going to do is integrate over the
wave band of interest using this discrete
equation or that differential
equation, I guess I should say,
to estimate...
Whoops, I went a little too far there, .36.
The area under the curve up to .36 and then
compare it to the total area under the curve.
So you should get similar results between problems Two
and three,
but they won't be exact because we've made major assumptions
in both cases. In the first case, we assumed that the first
part of that graph was a straight line approximation.
In number three, we assumed the sun acted
as a perfect black body. And
neither of those, so which do you think might be more accurate?
Again, provide your rationale.
Okay, moving on to heat transfer.
What do you think the hot to cold ratio is, or the hot to
cold-- How much can the temperature vary between just
hot and cold in Colorado Springs? And if you're not in Colorado
Springs, equate it to wherever you are.
Usually about five to 10 degrees Celsius difference, which
is pretty significant.
Day to day can be,
especially in Colorado Springs, geez,
plus or minus 30 degrees Celsius difference.
In orbit, like was mentioned in some of the earlier
presentations, we get severe thermal cycles.
We can go from 100 degrees C to
260 degrees C,
which is -150
Fahrenheit to 500 Fahrenheit.
So those are some pretty extreme temperature
differences. You must also account for any thermal
heat that's generated and what you should
do,
most of the time in my homework and exam problems, I'm
going to specify whether it's thermal heat or
strict power generation. If I only give you
a power generation number, then
assume the heat generated from that is about 10% of
the power. That should be very rare, but we will
be using it today on the in-class exercise.
Most of the time, I will specify that this is
heat-generating
energy.
So how does this work?
First off,
we have several governing equations.
We're going to equate our heat in equal
to our heat out.
First law of thermodynamics, energy in equals energy out,
assuming no losses, which is not necessarily a
good assumption, but that's the best we can do.
Qn
for solar, for example, is alpha
San,
where alpha is the absorptivity.
See if I can spell that. Yep, I sure can.
S is the solar flux at Earth. Since we're
dealing mostly with Earth-orbiting missions, that is
1367 watts per square meter,
and this would be the area
that the sun impacts.
Usually, for rough order estimates, we assume
one side. So we assume sun comes in one side, Earth comes in
the other side, Earth IR comes in the other side,
and you emit on all sides.
And then Qout
is emissivity
area
Boltzmann's constant times temperature to the fourth.
So let's define a few of these. Emissivity,
area
over
total
heat
expenditure.
Sigma is Boltzmann's constant, different from KB.
This is a different Boltzmann's constant, although I think it's attributed to
the same person,
5.67 times 10 to the minus 8
watt per meter squared Kelvin to the fourth,
and temperature is in Kelvin,
given Boltzmann's constant in Kelvin.
So usually the differences between the Qins,
those will typically be one side
coming in. The Qouts will be all
sides, unless there's insulation on one or the other
on some of the sides. That will typically be all six sides.
Okay. These are some of our thermal inputs.
Direct solar, 1367.
Varies depending on whether we're at perigee, at least in the
northern hemisphere, in the
winter, or apogee in the summer.
And these are some of the inputs. We get albedo, which
is the effect of the sun bouncing off the Earth.
We get the fact that the Earth has some temperature above zero Kelvin.
We get Earth infrared. And then we have internally
generated heat. If you have humans on board-
That adds about 100 watts per person,
just as a side note, in case you're doing analysis on that.
So how do we get those albedo numbers?
Well, it's an average across all Earth surfaces.
It would be very complicated to try to say, okay, we're over water, forest, sand,
ice or snow, clouds.
So what we do is we use an average.
Land is about 0.05 to
0.45 or 5% to 45%.
Water is about 3% to 20%. Clouds are about 10% to
80%, and snow is about 70% to 90%.
For the average, we use 34%,
which is how we came up with that previous number,
34%, as an average over the Earth.
Challenges are that, of
course,
we can get extreme hot, extreme
cold. Oops, I can't spell extreme.
Cycles,
which depending on the material's
thermal expansion factor, can make a big difference in material
strength. It can result in cracking or failure of
parts.
A variety of different materials with
different thermal expansion rates.
We have a variety of different components.
Usually, your tightest constraint
will be your batteries.
Batteries are typically
zero. As we know in Colorado,
batteries don't like it when you get less than zero to 30 degrees
C or too hot.
If you have an IR sensor on board, IR
sensors detect heat, so you have to keep
them cold so you can
actually see the heat
characteristics instead of your own
heating. And to give you an idea, in
Fahrenheit, minus 283
Fahrenheit to
minus 460. So they have to be kept very
cold, and there's ways that we can do that, too.
As an example, I just picked the Raptor engine, which is
used by SpaceX on Falcon 9.
It is
liquid oxygen and liquid methane.
To give you an idea of the temperature differences, the liquid
oxygen and liquid methane have to be kept at minus
162.
Roughly, or minus 258 degrees
Fahrenheit.
But combustion
in the same engine can reach temperatures up
to 1,800 degrees Celsius.
So think about the material properties of the
components that you're designing, and that is
3,300
degrees Fahrenheit.
So what are the principles of heat transfer?
Convection, conduction, radiation. That's what we got here on Earth.
Convection. Is convection going to work?
Well, we don't have a whole lot of air up there, so that's not going to help a
lot. Conduction often relies on
energy transfer through matter without fluid motion, and
a lot of times it relies on gravity.
Radiators or radiation is
really the only effective means of removing
heat from a satellite.
And one thing that we can do is shown over here.
These are called radiators with louvers.
We can open and close those louvers.
Say there's radiation
substance beneath that. Now we can open up those
louvers like window shades to either keep in the
heat if you're in the eclipse, you want a low
emissivity or
increase the emissivity if you're on the sun side, and
that often provides some of the best protection that we
can get.
We can also use coolants, coolant loops
internal to the spacecraft,
ammonia loops. You can even use wicking,
which will help.
But you have to make sure you
keep everything within your operating temperature range.
So the operating temperature is the Range that the
device can operate safely and meet its performance and
reliability specifications. The survival temperature
range means it'll still operate, but just not
as effectively.
So the basics of thermal control.
Thermal energy can either be transmitted, absorbed, or
reflected, and those percentages all have to add up
to 100%.
For Earth, the transmit ability is low.
There's not a whole lot that's going to be traveling through the Earth to
transmit the energy back out. But
absorptivity for Earth
is about 34%, and
absorptivity is about 66%
for Earth.
Your energy out, I already talked about this, I defined all those
terms.
Again, assumes no major losses. And make sure you
use your temperature in Kelvin.
For a black body, which sometimes we have to assume
we get absorptivity and emissivity
equal to 100%, absorbs 100% of what comes in,
emits 100%. No substance can really do that,
but we can approximate that with some types of insulation.
And actually, the human body is a pretty good approximation of
that, although we don't emit quite as much.
So for a black body, 100% of what comes
in, let's just draw a little graphic here.
Q in equals Q out.
100% absorbed.
100%
emitted.
So for example, a black paint acts
as almost a perfect
black body.
White paint
has low
absorptivity,
but a high emissivity, so a high ability
to dissipate the heat. So that's why you don't want to
wear black shirts in the
summer
because it's absorbing all of that heat.
Although it's dissipating a lot of it, you're still going to get what's leftover.
Whereas white T-shirts in the summer
are better because you get less
absorption, more emissivity.
In reality, though, these are very
dependent upon the wavelength at which
the energy is coming from.
So here's a
graphic of
emissions for white paint, or emissivity for white paint
over the frequency spectrum.
For high
emissivity in the infrared range,
it's pretty good. In the higher regions, it's pretty bad,
although you can get some drop-off up towards the,
that would be towards the wider regions, the less...
What's the word I'm looking for? Less colorful regions.
And
some drops in the
visible range, but out in the higher frequency
ranges, it's pretty constant. It tends to drop off a little bit
as you get into the very
low frequency ranges,
or long wavelengths.
Okay. So I provide this as a little experiment for you to do on your
own. If you want to see how well white
transmits energy, you can see that it
will transmit these lower frequencies, but these
higher frequencies,
it will not
transmit as
well. And you can do that just by taking a
projector or even taking your computer screen, putting a white piece of paper
over it, you'll see that it transmits the reds, yellows,
greens, and light blues well, but the ones towards the
right, which we can see by this,
it drops off significantly in the blue and purple ranges,
and you will see those transmit through the piece of paper as
nearly black. So that is
showing how this
variation with
frequency and wavelength works.
So these are our equations. We have four main components.
We've got solar, albedo,
infrared, and internal, and that's equal to Q
emitted. So equating those, we can get an equilibrium
temperature. Now, we don't consider time in this case.
That would be a completely different equation
And it's still an important factor, but for the purposes of this
class, we're going to assume we have time to meet
equilibrium temperature. Otherwise, we'd have to figure out
capacitances and things beyond the scope of this
course.
So Q solar,
you take the absorptivity
times the area in
times the solar flux, and that gives you your Q solar.
Q albedo depends on the sun angle that we have been
talking about before. You can tell from here that the
sine of the sun angle is
the radius of the Earth, this radius, divided
by
the radius of the Earth plus
altitude.
And you use that here to calculate the
albedo, and I don't know how they came up with the sine squared term.
That would be an area of future research.
And then Q IR has the same factor there, sine squared of
rho,
where the albedo flux and the IR flux are both
given. And we're going to use for the radius of the Earth
6,378 kilometers to
be consistent.
That's an average. It varies depending on where you are in
latitude.
These are the average albedos for planets,
and you will need this for homework
problem four. Yeah, four.
I'll get to that in a minute.
Now,
that being said,
the
absorption to emissivity rate
varies also dependent on temperature.
So this is not an easy linear relationship or anything
like that.
This says that the change in
absorptivity for emissivity is four times
the change in the temperature,
your original
absorptivity to
emissivity ratio divided by the temperature.
So it's very dependent on temperature also.
We're not going to do any calculations on that in this class,
but it is definitely pertinent to this discussion.
Okay.
Let's go to the homework problem first, and then
I'll do an example
on how you calculate equilibrium temperatures.
NASA's designing an interplanetary probe to
investigate Eris,
which is a dwarf planet
that goes beyond Pluto, but it also
sometimes comes inside Neptune's
trajectory or Neptune's orbit. And what I'm
asking you to do is to, based on the
requirement that your
high-resolution camera needs to stay between -35
to 35 degrees Celsius, what planets can it
image
with equilibrium temperatures that go within
those parameters?
We're going to say that for the sake of this, one
side
is
orbiting the sun or one side is facing the sun,
and then the other side is facing the planet
for the purposes of this. And then you'll look into both
the eclipse
and the sun side
generation and see what equilibrium temperatures.
So I ask you to plot the equilibrium temperatures for each of
the planets and recommend a thermal control system.
So let's take a look at this
exercise here. We have a
one cubic meter. I made that an easy dimension there.
At an altitude of 100 kilometers and an inclination of
zero degrees. I made that also
easy to work with. The satellite internal components
generate 500 watts of heat,
not 500 watts of power. I specifically called that
heat, at all times during its
five-year mission life. Assume
body-mounted solar arrays on four sides of the spacecraft.
Identify its steady state temperatures during sunlight and eclipse
periods. Assume solar arrays.
The other two sides, let's kind of draw this
out.
I have assumed this. So these are my solar array sides.
This is insulation,
and the bottom is also insulation.
And one side faces the sun, obviously not to
scale. One side faces the Earth.
So how can we find that?
And we also want to keep between zero and 35 degrees C.
So let's see if we meet those requirements, and if not, we'll take
a look at what to do about that. So on the
sun side,
we have the following inputs. Q solar
Plus
Q Earth IR,
plus
Q albedo,
plus Q internal
is equal to the output,
which we defined as that before.
So to find each component, we've got Q
solar is alpha area
times solar flux.
Or let's see, our absorptivity
is 0.975.
Area, based on the way I've drawn this here in my
assumptions, and when you do your homework problem, clearly
state your assumptions. We've got one side,
so one meter squared,
times the input from the sun, 1367
watts per meter squared. So that gives me a value in watts
of
1332.83
watts.
Q albedo I'll do next since it's related to the sun,
is alpha A
sine squared rho
times the albedo flux.
Where rho is the inverse sine
of 6378 divided by
6378 plus
1,000,
and you will get 59.82
degrees.
So you plug that into here with the same
absorptivity, 0.975.
sine squared, don't forget the squared term, of
59.82 times the albedo
flux,
which is 465.
You get 338.8 watts.
Almost there. Q IR
is alpha A sine
squared rho times,
237.
I'll let you work out the math there for yourself.
It will be 172.7
watts.
Okay, so we're ready to solve. We've got Q
total
is all these summed together.
We also have Q internal is 500
watts.
So you total all those up, you get
on the hot side,
2344.3
is equal to
emissivity, 0.85,
times 5.67 times 10 to the minus 8
Boltzmann's constant,
times four sides. Remember, we got insulation on the top and
bottom. We're assuming that they
do not allow any heat in or out, so we're emitting
over four sides.
T to the fourth, we can solve that for an equilibrium
temperature of
332.1K.
Subtract 273.15 from that, we
get 59.1 degrees Celsius.
Is that within our range? No, it's not.
Greater than 35. Okay. So we're going to have to do
something about that. Let's take a look at the eclipse side.
Now we eliminate the sun
and albedo.
So we're left with
672.7
watts is equal to the same expression.
Now we get T is equal
to
243.05
Kelvin or
minus 30 approximately, rounding off, 30 degrees
Celsius. That is not within our limit, so that's less
than zero degrees. So that's a concern, too.
So I went through that very quick, but I wanted
to give you an idea of how to solve these type of
problems.
Now, what can we do about this? Now, I typically do this as
an in-class exercise, and it usually takes students
about an hour to do this.
So I'm going to
work through this with you so that it doesn't
take until the full amount of time is up
to show what a good solution will
be. So some components, some things you can do, materials
and coatings, multilayer insulation, radiators.
These are all passive. You don't need any active or power
control to use these. And typically, passive
techniques can take care of about 80% of all
thermal control activities.
Not all of it, though, and we'll find that in this case.
Active elements, I already talked about louvers opening and closing,
like window blinds.
Heaters can be used. Those are often the first two
I would go to. If you're dealing with cryo systems,
refrigeration or cooling systems, or thermoelectric
coolers for cryo, but otherwise, you probably wouldn't
have to worry about those. And of course, you'll need temperature sensors
and thermostats to
determine
when to turn heaters on and off, for example.
So the process is you go through defining the
requirements. We know our requirement is 0 to 35
degrees Celsius. Determine the thermal environment.
We just did that. We said it was between
minus 30 and 59.1 degrees Celsius.
Problem. So what do we do?
Typical operating temperatures, like I said before, your
tightest will probably be batteries.
I've given you a bit of a
leeway
on this particular exercise so that we're not here like
for four hours trying to figure out a solution.
Insulation. This is giving you-- Insulation really
does not have no emissivity. It has about
0.05 emissivity because no insulator is
perfect. So keep that in mind. That's different from our previous
assumption, where emissivity and absorptivity were both
zero. And then these are the values for
radiators. Radiators with louvers have variable emissivity.
So when they're closed, that would be 0.05, close to
0.05. When they're completely open, close
to 0.8. And I do see an
error on this. This should be
kilograms. No, that's right.
That's right. Yeah.
And then we have...
Let's see, where are my heaters?
Heaters. Okay. They're in kilograms per watt. That's good. All right.
So we can use these. So for example,
now you're given $400,000 to design a thermal control system.
You have the following choices. Each kilogram of mass
adds $25,000 to the cost of the mission.
And you're given absorptivities of
the white paint, black paint. You're given no
absorptivity for the radiators, the radiators with
louvers, but according to Kirchhoff's law, yes, the same
Kirchhoff that had the electronic
KVL and KCL.
If you're looking for an absorptivity and
you're not given one,
usually for radiators and radiators with louvers, you can
use the same as the emissivity. Those are approximately
equal.
Okay.
So let's start by
working this problem.
Now,
on the cold side, we know we don't meet requirements.
And that's where I would start. You could start with the hot side, fix that,
but I think by putting in our solution for the cold side,
we'll be there a little faster. I'm trying to get through this exercise
a little fast. It would probably take you,
like I said before, it usually takes my undergraduate students an
hour, so it'd probably take y'all about 30 minutes to come up with a
solution to this.
So
neither requirement is met. So we're going to
have to use some variable emissivity, which means radiators
with louvers. So let's check the cold side.
We've got 676.7 or what was
it before? That's not right.
672.7.
And that is equal to
0.05. We've got two sides covered
with insulation,
plus
0.85
times 4
times 5.67 times 10 to the minus
8 t to the 4th, and that says we're
at, which we decided before, about minus
31 degrees C
or 30 degrees C.
No good.
So
the question now becomes: how much heat would we
need
to meet the minimum temperature requirement?
And I'm not going to go for zero degrees.
I'm going to add a little bit of margin in there and make it
1.5 degrees Celsius. So at
672.7
Notice
that if we're using louvers,
we have a requirement to add two watts per each
side. But that would essentially, if you take
10% of that, that would be 0.2. I'm just treating that as
mostly negligible. It's not a whole lot of power.
So I'm leaving this out of our equations here.
So 672.7
plus the heater
is equal to 3.5
times
Boltzmann's constant. I had to look that up.
So I picked that to purposely be 1.5 degrees
Celsius. Give me a little bit of margin.
And the reason I picked that is because I know that's going to fit within my
budget requirement. You would probably have to go through a couple of
iterations to narrow it down to that.
So that says the heater
must be about 450 watts.
So that would be the way I would approach that problem.
Solve for the cold first, determine how
many heaters. The heaters, you would only turn on during the
eclipse, then you turn them off when you're on the sun side.
Often I get questions, "Why do you want to turn them off at all?" Well, two
reasons.
The hot side will be even hotter, and we're already out of bounds
for
the equilibrium temperature of 35 degrees
Celsius. The second is that you save power by
not having them on in the sunlight, and that can be a
very valuable asset, or very valuable
if you are trying to minimize power.
Okay, so if we check our equilibrium temperature,
we will see that it's 1.5 degrees C now.
Now let's check it in the sun. So we had
2344.3
is equal to
0.85 times four sides. And
now remember, I have radiators with louvers, so I'm going to put
up 0.8. Let's see. Yeah, that's the highest
I can go, times two.
That totals up to five, by the way,
times 5.67 times 10 to the
minus
8 T to the fourth. And with that
lower emissivity
of... Wait a minute, something's wrong here.
Yeah, that's good.
We get
301.7 K or
about 28.7 degrees Celsius.
So that meets specifications.
So by just adding those two simple additions,
radiators with louvers
and
heaters, we can solve our thermal equilibrium
temperature requirements. So if we check the cost,
let's see. Do I have another page here? Check cost.
We had $400,000 to work within.
We have radiators with louvers.
We had 2.1 kilogram per meter squared
times two meters squared,
plus
0.2
times two
meters squared.
We've got times 25,000.
We have 115,000 for the radiators with
louvers, and then for the heaters,
we've got 0.025,
which I get from here, times 450 watts
times 2500.
I mean, is equal to 2500.
So 115 or 25,000, I mean
115 plus...
No, I meant times 25,000
is equal to
281,250.
So those added up together give me
396,250,
and hence I am within my budget.
Okay.
So that was my last thermal control example.
Now, in the next block, we're going to go into contamination
control, and I've only probably got 30 minutes left to go.
So,
anyone have any comments or questions on that?
I did have a quick question. So the values that you
presented,
can we use those for our project, or should we find
other
values?
The emissivities and absorptivities?
Yeah.
Yeah, that would be fine. Those are pretty standard.
All right. Thank you.
Yeah. Good question.
Okay, part two.
Contamination.
And the presenters today had some excellent examples
of how to prevent contamination, but I wanted to start
off with
what is contamination
and
where does it come from?
When I worked on the Titan IV program,
I was working in a division that handled the
mechanical stuff, loads and dynamics,
vibration, contamination,
acoustics. There was a lieutenant
assigned for the launch vehicle strictly to work on
contamination, that's how important it was, and contamination
control
programs or plans.
And that was how important it was. One lieutenant was
handling probably a 15-person
department at our prime contractor, which was Martin
Marietta at the time.
So that's how important contamination is because, I'll
show some examples, these can be definite
problems. So according to dictionary.com,
contamination
is, couple of different definitions here, the
action or state
of making
or being made impure.
So that's the definition we'll use, by
polluting,
polluting is a good word,
or poisoning. We're not going to take a look at too much of
that.
Hopefully, poisoning to me implies intentional.
Merriam-Webster says to soil,
stain,
corrupt,
or infect
by contact
or association.
That implies more human involvement, so we're going to concentrate on the
contact part.
So the definition that I like using for this
class is to make
impure
or unclean.
And the difference between the two is impure
would be mostly caused by a chemical reaction,
and unclean would be by foreign particles
or foreign substances or grease or oils from
hands or something like that.
So coming up are some examples of what you want to
avoid happening.
Solar Max Kapton surfaces. Got them a nice
wipe-down, cleaned
surfaces, but it didn't help with
contamination once it got into space.
So, UV exposure brought
out the droplets that were left behind, even
microscopic,
of the cleaning fluid, and it ended
up contaminating
that surface.
It was in LEO at 28 and a half degrees, and
it was intended to
investigate solar phenomena, but it was taken
out. It was launched in, what year?
February of 1989,
and it was killed by March of '89 by
geomagnetic storms, and it eventually deorbited
a few months later in December of '89.
So not the greatest example of a successful
experiment.
Second example, why we bunny suit up when we go into clean rooms.
You can see the fingerprints here of people left, just the oil in their
fingers. And when it
goes into space, you can see
that
it looks like contamination, or it looks like there's something
there. So that's not a good sign
either. So that's why we bunny suit up when we go into clean
rooms, is to make sure we're not getting our hair or body
oils or whatever on the equipment.
Types of contamination. Molecular
means interactions or outgassing particulate
physical dirt, hand oils,
biological humans or biological species
on other planets, or bringing harmful substances back to the
Earth. Now, I don't spend a lot of time talking about that in this class,
but I do have an example here. This was
taken from a water droplet that was
just floating there on the mirror,
and they probably didn't have as strict standards as we do
now on the ISS, but you can see just the water
and the human life involvement there,
provided these microbiomes plenty of room
to multiply.
So as this course is mostly on Earth-orbiting satellites,
we'll focus mostly on molecular and
particulates.
So molecular... Oh, let me go back to the pictures.
These are pictures of typical contaminants.
In the middle there,
on the right there is a new coating that NASA adopted
or developed. I don't know if they're flying it yet, but anyway, they developed
it that traps outgas material, and then
I already talked about the floating mirror
grossness.
It can be liquid, solid, or gas, and it can either be
uniform or non-uniform. Those are five basic categories.
Outgassing.
This was talked about a lot in today's presentation, so I'm not
going to go into this a whole lot.
But
basically, excess chemicals can be left over from
improper catalyst or
ratios.
Excuse me.
Or improper curing here on the Earth, and they migrate to the
surface, and that's actually what a new car smell is.
You leave it out in the sun, you get your UV rays coming in.
You can get that outgassing,
which is why your car smells new in the beginning,
especially if you leave it out in the sun.
Outgassing can affect thermal properties, optical
devices,
degraded performance such as solar arrays, and can create
surface reactions. So those chemicals
will migrate to the surface, and then once the electrical
attraction to the surface of the material has been broken, then that
outgassing occurs, and that can contaminate other
surfaces. What are the
ways of variation? How can it vary exponentially as
a function of time, inversely as a power of time, or independently of
time? Trick question. The answer is all three.
Desorption
is mostly exponentially as a function of
time,
and it tends to look something like this over time.
If this is time,
oops,
and this is mass, you would expect that as time goes
off, the amount of mass that you're losing would go down.
Inversely as a proportion of the time, this is through
diffusion,
and that would be transport of molecules with
concentration gradient. So
if you have a high concentration of
molecules, it's going to want to move towards the low
concentration.
Desorption is very low
energy.
This is medium energy.
And it looks similar to, it's like a function of one over
square root of t. It is inversely
related to that t, and it
looks similar to number one, except it slopes off a little
less steeply.
And then we already talked about independently of time.
We talked about decomposition at the beginning of
this
lecture.
High energy
So actually, all three can be part
of outgassing, so it can get very complicated very quickly.
Mostly outgassing varies with time.
Desorption and diffusion require lower energy levels, and
I have a synopsis here, so I'm not going to write these down.
But from about one to 10 kilocalories per mole,
or about, maybe I should write this here, one to
10... Oh, I have the electron volts there.
This varies according to one over T or one over ND12.
Diffusion, which is shown here where these
particles move up to the surface,
that is a medium phenomena, medium energy
phenomena.
And that is usually greater than
about 0.2 electron volts.
And then decomposition, we already studied
is where a compound divides into two or
more simpler substances, then they outgas, and that is
independent of time. That just happens.
Oh, let me see.
I didn't think the video would work. Okay.
So, an example of that is a mission I worked on when I was
a lieutenant, is the Cassini mission, and
it went to Saturn and investigated
Huygens probe to investigate Saturn's moon,
Titan. And we found some absolutely fascinating
information about Titan,
which is why we're getting ready to fly the Dragonfly mission back there in a few
years. But on the way out
there, we're thinking, "Oh, okay, everything's looking good.
We got Saturn in our sights."
Thirteen months later, we got that.
And you would think it would get clearer as you got closer to Saturn.
Well, obviously something happened between picture one and picture
two,
and
that was due to outgassing.
Contamination, that caused contamination.
Fortunately, we had two heaters attached to the radiators,
which were turned on to heat charge couple devices, which
basically convert incoming photons into electrons
using capacitors to provide digital imaging.
So these are digital images.
And it went from -90 degree Celsius to
-30 degree Celsius in six
hours. And we saw it slowly start
to
dissipate the contamination and we eventually, and I think it's even a
little clearer here, although it should be after that many months,
the final picture of Saturn. Saturn in
view
on the right-hand side. And that,
we just got very fortunate that we had those heaters on board.
If we had not thought ahead of that process, ahead
of that happening, then we could have very well got no
useful information from Cassini.
There is a NASA outgassing database, and one of the
speakers today, I don't remember which one, referred to
TML and CBCM.
Another measure is WVR,
and I'll explain what those are in just a minute in a couple of
slides. Total mass loss,
I'll talk about those in a couple of minutes.
So measured outgassing rates, how are these determined?
Well, mostly experimentally. The outgassing rate is
equal to this equation. We don't use that, or at least I'm not going to
ask you to use it for this class.
We are going to use this expression.
So if you want to know the outgassing,
it's usually measured by bake out in a thermal
vac chamber.
And one thing to note,
it's given in watts per meter squared, but these
units are torr liters per centimeter squared
second. So one of the first things you're going to look
into in your homework is
how the outgassing rate of watts per meter squared, which
is what you want, is related to the outgassing rate
in torr liter centimeter per centimeter squared second.
And a torr, by the way, is one
divided by 760th of a standard
atmosphere, which is 101.3 kilopascals.
M dot is the mass loss per unit area per time.
M is the molar mass, which can sometimes be hard to
tell, unless it's
a
element that we know the molar mass for.
And NA is Avogadro's constant, and
that is, oh, I guess I didn't write it down here.
That is equal to 6.022
times 10 to the 23, one per
kilomole.
Or what would that be? 6.022 hexillion.
Or
I didn't mean or. This will be very important for your homework
problem number,
I think we're up to six.
Notes on using this model. Most data comes from
measured data,
so it's empirical.
Yes, we can model. We can measure outgassing, but
what if we want to model it?
It's very challenging because quite often the mass
flow rate and n dot
outgassing particle rate are not known.
And again,
the molar mass is difficult... Going the wrong way.
Molar mass of outgassing particles is difficult to
measure unless it's a pure element.
So let's go into a little bit more about each of these
methods. Desorption is the release of surface
molecules, and one thing to note, some
texts will say it's an
exponential function. That is not what we're going to do in this
class.
So m dot is minus m over t, and that
is the outgassing rate per unit area
in kilogram per meter squared second.
Tau is the residence time. It's like a
discharge time for electrical components or RC circuits
if you're into circuits.
T naught
is given by H over kBT, so you need to know the
temperature of the substance, and that
would be in Kelvin. Let me write that down.
So
m dot, let me see if I have this on the next page.
Nope, I don't. M dot
is equal to minus
m over tau and t naught is given by
that, so we got m over
tau
naught e to the minus Ea
over RT.
So m as a function of t is
m naught e to the minus t
over tau.
So that's the bottom line. It's an exponentially decaying
function, kind of like that.
And it's still not very well understood.
Diffusion, on the other hand, is a little
more well understood. It's equal to that
expression there. Q naught is reaction constant, and you have a whole
reference here to provide those.
And Ea is activation
energy in kilocalories per mole.
So what are these TMLs, CVCMs, and
WVRs? Well, the TML is called total mass
loss, and that is the amount of material that
outgasses from a sample held at
125 degrees Celsius for 24
hours when the density is low or less than
seven times 10 to the minus three pascals.
CVCM is collected volatile condensable
material. How much is outgassed on a collection plate at 25 degrees
Celsius. And water vapor regained is how much
mass is gained when test sample put at 50% relative
humidity at 23 degrees Celsius
for 24 hours.
So those are some measures that you can use
to evaluate whether your material is going to outgas and how
severely. Homework problem five.
I do give you
the
factor that changes watts to meters squared,
7.5 times 10 to the minus 4 into torl liter centimeter
squared second.
But you have to show that in the homework.
And then the number of molecules released per unit
area per second, we solve
the outgassing equation for n dot, and we
get Q of t over
kBT.
So that should be a pretty straightforward problem there, and you're
given the temperature.
Okay, next time we're going to look at
particulate con-- No, not particulate contamination.
This is an outdated slide, I guess, or I have a typo in there.
We're going to look at radiation environment,
and
that's going to involve both human effects
spacecraft effects. So single event upsets, there's a lot
of different categories of that. Also human effects.
What is the difference between rads, radiation biological
equivalent, and rems, R-E-M-S? So we'll
look at some of those effects next time. All right.
That's all I have tonight. We'll see you all next Thursday,
and thank you for your time. If anyone wants to hang around and ask questions,
please do.
I did have a quick question.
Let me turn off recording.
Okay.